Inventory of the Benjamin C. Willis papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Minutes from school board meeting of Broward County, Florida, 1970-1971 (Box 227)
- Minutes from school board meeting of Broward County, Florida, 1970-1971 (Box 228)
- Correspondence, 1979 April-December (Box 228)
- Correspondence, 1980 January-February (Box 228)
- Correspondence, 1980 March-December (Box 229)
- Chicago Board of Education, 1965 (Box 229)
  Includes miscellaneous correspondence.
- Pension and retirement funds, 1961 (Box 229)
- Clippings, transcripts of hearings, and school survey committee materials, 1955-1965 (Box 230)
- Notes, press releases, and newsletters, 1965 (Box 231)
- Chicago Board of Education. Materials from Fiscal Policy meetings, 1963 (Box 232)
- Reports and statements to Chicago Board of Education, 1963-1964 (Box 232)
- Reports and enrollment figures, 1963-1964 (Box 233)
- Office files regarding education and events, 1964 (Box 234)
- Magazines, 1965-1966 (Box 234)
  Includes articles on Willis.
- Magazines and clippings, 1951, 1965 (Box 235)
- Photographs of Willis, 1950s-1960s (Box 235)
- Photographs of Vocational Conference, 1960s (Box 235)
- Magazines and clippings, 1951-1966 (Box 236)
- Photographs, 1932 (Box 236)
- Clippings, arranged by subject, 1950s (Box 237)
- Photo album of conference testimonies, 1959-1961 (Box 237)
- Photographs with President John F. Kennedy, circa 1962 (Box 237)
- Photo album of graduation exercises for Chicago City College, 1961 June (Box 238)
- Reports and studies, 1967 (Box 238)
- News clippings, 1966 (Box 238)
- News clippings, 1953-1967 (Box 239)
- News clippings, 1955 (Box 240)
- Chicago Retired Teachers. Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 240)
- Chicago Retired Teachers. Expenses and miscellaneous (Box 241)
- Committee by-laws and related papers, 1979-1981 (Box 241)
- Papers relating to A. Maxim Coppage, 1979-1981 (Box 241)
- Papers relating to A. Maxim Coppage, 1979-1981 (Box 242)
- Empty photo albums (Box 243)
- Enhance, nutritional supplement company, undated (Box 244)
  Order forms and correspondence
- Meadowfresh company forms (Box 244)
- Meadowfresh, presentation packets, undated (Box 245)
  Includes audio cassette tape labeled "Napkin Presentation."
- Miscellaneous catalogs and mail order forms, 1980s (Box 245)
- Miscellaneous directories and mailing lists, 1980s (Box 245)
- Chicago Public Schools and Chicago Board of Education. Curriculum and training guides (Box 246)
- Profiles of schools in Florida, 1972 (Box 246)
- Reports, studies, and surveys, 1958-1972 (Box 246)
- Reports, studies, and surveys, 1958-1972 (Box 247)
- Yearbook, 1964 (Box 247)
- Printed matter, 1974 (Box 247)
- Illinois Junior College, 1967-1969 (Box 248)
- University of Illinois, 1967-1969 (Box 248)
- Chicago Association of Commerce and Industry, 1967-1968 (Box 249)
- The Bridge, educational organization, 1967-1968 (Box 249)
- The Bridge. Studies and correspondence, 1967 (Box 250)
- Chicago Boys Club. Correspondence, 1967 (Box 250)
- Chicago Boys Club, 1969 (Box 251)
- Scholarship program materials (Box 251)
- Cosmetology Accreditation Committee papers, 1967 (Box 251)
- Cosmetology program, 1968 (Box 252)
- Educational Policy commission meeting materials, 1957 (Box 253)
- Steering committee meetings, 1958 (Box 253)
- Educational Policy commission meeting materials, 1958 (Box 254)
- Educational Policy commission meeting materials, 1959-1960 (Box 255)
- Educational Policy commission conference materials, 1959-1961 (Box 256)
- Educational Policy commission conference materials, 1959-1961 (Box 257)
- School surveys, 1963-1964 (Box 257)
- School surveys, 1964 (Box 258)
- Report of conference proceedings, 1955 (Box 258)
- Special Project study papers, 1960 (Box 259)
- Reports of the Professional Conference of Chicago Public School Administrators, 1956-1960 (Box 259)
- Education studies. Massachusetts public education research materials, 1963-1965 (Boxes 260-262)
- Illinois Junior College Board minutes, 1967 (Box 263)
- Binders. Principals meetings at Teacher's College, Columbia University (Box 264)
  Includes charts.
- Writings and essays by Willis, 1950 (Box 265)
- Correspondence, 1947 (Box 265)
- Student essay contest submissions, 1948 (Box 265)
  Essay topic is "The American Way of Life--It's Meaning for Me." Sent to Willis' office as superintendent of schools in Yonkers, New York
- Student essay contest submissions, 1948 (Box 266)
- Chicago Board of Education. Financial reports, 1954 (Box 266)
- Chicago Board of Education. Financial reports, 1952-1953 (Box 267)
- Student essay contest submissions, 1948 (Box 267)
- Yonkers, New York superintendent files, 1955-1957 (Box 268)
  Includes datebooks.
- Datebooks, 1954-1965 (Box 269)
- Datebooks, 1965-1966 (Box 270)
- Chicago Board of Education. Official report, 1950 (Box 270)
- Chicago Board of Education. Annual budget, 1951, 1964 (Box 270)
- Chicago Board of Education. Annual budget and financial reports, 1955-1957 (Box 271)
- Chicago Board of Education. Annual budget and financial reports, 1957-1959 (Box 272)
- Chicago Board of Education. Annual budget and financial reports, 1959-1961 (Box 273)
- Chicago Board of Education. Annual budget and financial reports, 1961-1963 (Box 274)
- Correspondence and personal files, 1940s (Box 275)
- Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 276)
- Studies, summaries, and correspondence, 1940s (Box 277)
- Correspondence, 1930s-1940s (Box 278)
- Notes from faculty meetings, 1930s-1940s (Box 278)
- Monthly supervisory reports, 1931 (Box 278)
- Correspondence and notes, 1930-1933 (Box 279)
- Notes, notebooks, and correspondence, 1931-1938 (Box 280)
- Dr. Paul R. Mort, correspondence, 1943 (Box 280)
- Personal file, 1940 (Box 280)
- Personal file and correspondence, 1949 (Box 281)
- Bound hardcopy of Vocational Education Act, 1963 (Box 281)
- Standard Education Almanac, 1974-1975 (Box 282)
- Monographs, 1937-1976 (Box 282)
  Monographs in boxes 282 to 301 include works of fiction and non-fiction on the topics of American history, education, educational administration, professional development, and management. Most are inscribed with a note to Willis from the author
- Report of the Survey of the Schools of Chicago Illinois, Volumes 1-5, 1932 (Box 283)
- Report of Warren Commission, 1964 (Box 283)
- Monographs, 1937-1976 (Box 283)
- Monographs, 1937-1976 (Boxes 284-300)
- Monographs, 1960s (Box 301)
- Great Cities program file, 1966 (Box 301)
- Chicago Board of Education. Reports and statements, 1966 (Box 302)
- Correspondence, 1966 January-July (Box 303)
- Correspondence, 1966 August (Box 304)
- Miscellaneous papers. Correspondence and conference materials, 1966 (Box 305)
- Chicago Board of Education. Studies and reports, 1965-1966 (Box 306)
- Reports to Chicago Board of Education by Willis, 1964-1965 (Box 306)
- Reports to Chicago Board of Education by Willis, 1966 (Box 307)
- Correspondence with Kiwanis Club, 1966-1967 (Box 307)
- Advisory Committee on Education, 1966 (Box 307)
- Reports to Chicago Board of Education by Willis, 1965-1966 (Box 308)
- Commission on Life Adjustment Education for Youth. Conference materials, reports, and correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 309)
- Commission on Life Adjustment Education for Youth. Conference materials, reports, and correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 310)
- Commission on Life Adjustment Education for Youth. Conference materials, reports, and correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 311)
- White House conference report, 1966 (Box 311)
- Notes from meeting with Chicago Teacher's Union, 1966 (Box 311)
- Illinois Education Association Collective Bargaining Division, 1962-1963 (Box 312)
- Teacher salaries, 1965 (Box 312)
- Chicago Public Schools, general packets, brochures, and other materials, 1955-1964 (Box 313)
- "Selected Surveys and Studies with Implications for Guidance," reports, undated (Box 313)
- Reports on educational specifications for different schools in Chicago (Box 314)
- Civil rights, 1962 (Box 314)
- Central office communications, 1965 (Box 314)
- Inernational Bureau of Education, bulletins, 1967 (Box 315)
- Chicago Board of Education. Public hearing on budget, 1966 (Box 315)
- International Bureau of Education, 1964-1965 (Box 316)
- Buffalo School District files (Box 317)
- Research materials on city of Chicago, 1950s (Box 317)
  Includes real estate, population, and urban amenities.
- Correspondence, 1950s (Box 318)
- Report on desegregation in Florida, 1972 (Box 319)
- Study of public schools in Broward County, Florida, 1967 (Box 319)
- Journal of trip to Asia, circa 1950s (Box 320)
- Chicago Board of Education. Reports on budget, 1966 (Box 320)
- Chicago Board of Education. Annual budget, 1965 (Box 321)
- Transcripts of radio editorials, 1966 (Box 321)
- Financial reports, 1965 (Box 322)
- Verbatim transcripts. Meeting of the Special Committee on the Hauser Report on integration, 1964 June (Box 322)
- Board of Education. Evaluation of proposal regarding computers, 1962 (Box 322)
- Hauser report, 1964 (Box 323)
- Board of Education Official Committee meeting, 1960 (Box 323)
- Files relating to custodial service, 1959 (Box 323)
- Daily planners, 1963-1972 (Box 323)
- Reports published by Chicago Public Schools, 1964 (Box 324)
- Daily planners, 1973 (Box 325)
- Files relating to custodial service, 1958 (Box 325)
- Daily planners, 1947-1968 (Box 326)
- Nameplate, undated (Box 326)
- Address book, undated (Box 326)
- Yonkers, New York superintendent papers, 1940s-1950s (Box 327)
- AASA. Directories and meeting materials, 1980s (Box 328)
- Florida Association of School Administrators (FASA), 1982 (Box 329)
- Florida office files, 1980s (Box 329)
- Speaking engagements, 1940-1948 (Box 330)
- Yonkers, New York superintendent files, 1940s (Box 330)
  Includes correspondence, reports, and memoranda.
- Russell Sage Foundation project, 1965 (Box 330)
- Personal correspondence, 1947 (Box 331)
- Harvard visiting committee materials, 1961 (Box 331)
- Ford Foundation reports, 1962 (Box 331)
- Correspondence with committees, associations, and institutions, 1950s-1960s (Box 332)
- Correspondence with committees, associations, and institutions, 1950s-1960s (Box 333)
- Reports and writings on urbanization, 1962 (Box 333)
- Materials relating to the University of Chicago (Box 334)
- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 334)
- Reports and studies, 1961-1962 (Box 335)
- Building program, undated (Box 335)
- Report on enrollment, 1961 (Box 335)
- Reports to Board of Education, 1962 (Box 336)
  Includes reports on mobile classrooms.
- Reports to Board of Education, 1963 (Box 337)
- Verbatim transcripts. Board of Education meetings, 1963 (Box 337)
- Enhance, company product files, 1970s or 1980s (Box 337)
- Report. "Temporary Permissive Transfer Program to Relieve Overcrowding in Elementary Schools,", 1963 October (Box 337)
- Miscellaneous reports and office files, 1962-1965 (Box 338)
- Reports and statements to Board of Education, 1962-1963 (Box 339)
- Enhance, company product files, undated (Box 340)
  Includes brochure, information packets, and glass shampoo and lotion bottles.
- Enhance, company product files, undated (Box 341)
  Includes brochures on personal care products.
- Correspondence, 1953 (Box 342)
- 1945-1950s (Box 343)
  Includes miscellaneous correspondence, reports, and other materials.
- Binders of minutes regarding human relations work in Chicago schools, 1948-1951 (Box 344)
- School binders, 1940s (Box 344)
- 1950s (Box 345)
- 1950s (Box 346)
  Include files on education.
- General education files, 1951 (Box 347)
- Yearbook, 1921 (Box 348)
- Packets of automation studies by General Electric, undated (Box 348)
- Reports and writings by Willis, 1962 (Box 348)
- Monographs (Box 349)
- Bretney Corporation. Company packets on household products and nutritional supplements, 1982 (Box 350)
- Bretney Corporation files. Correspondence, 1982 (Box 351)
- Bretney Corporation files. Correspondence, 1980s (Box 352)
- The Educator's Encyclopedia (Box 353)
- Monographs on education, 1950s (Box 354)
- Bretney Corporation files, undated (Box 354)
- Miscellaneous personal correspondence, 1982 (Box 355)
- American Association of Retired Persons (AARP), 1980 (Box 355)
- Retirement files, 1980s (Box 355)
- Statements and reports to Board of Education, 1964 (Box 356)
- Speeches and speech materials, 1965 (Box 357)
- Photo album, 1961 Septemeber - 1962 August (Box 357)
- Photo album, 1957 January - 1959 June (Box 357)
- Photo albums, 1965-1966 (Box 358)
- Photo album, 1955 August - 1956 December (Box 359)
- Personal correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 359)
- Monographs, 1950s (Box 359)
- Reports and statements to Board of Education, 1963 (Boxes 360-361)
- Speeches and public statements, 1964 (Boxes 362-363)
- Oversize. Management Division of Academy for Education Development, 1959-1970 (Box 364)
  Includes box of conference materials, printed matter, and brochures.
- Oversize. News clippings and magazines, 1959-1964 (Box 365)
- Oversize. Photo album of publicity photographs of Willis, undated (Box 365)
- Oversize. Trophy from Fisher Body Craftsmen Guild Model Car Competition, marked "Advisory Board 1954-1967" (Box 366)
- Oversize. AASA member plaques, 1979-1982 (Box 367)
- Nameplates and empty photo albums (Box 367)
- "A Salute to Dr. Willis,", 1966 (Box 368)
- Your Right to Say It television program, 1961 November 28; 1.0 sound tape reel (Box 368)
  Broadcaster: WGN, Channel 9 Subject: Integration in the Chicago Schools Guests: John M. Fewkes, Rev. Carl A. Fuqua
- The Jerry Williams Show: "School Problems in Chicago,", 1965 October 25; 2 sound tape reels (Box 368)
- General committee meeting, 1966 April 13; 3 sound tape reels (Box 368)
  Though a five-part recording, only parts 2-4 are available.
- Policy hearing, 1966 April 14; 2 sound tape reels (Box 368)
- Regular board meeting, 1966 May 11; 2 sound tape reels (Box 368)
  Though a three-part recording, only parts 2-3 are available.
- Unidentified sound recordings, 1966; 2 sound tape reels (Box 368)
- Christmas program: Barton School chorus, Morgan Park High School chorus, 1965 December 16; 1 sound tape reel (Box 368)
- At Random television program, sound recording, 3 sound tape reels (Tape cabinet)
  Access
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0013417
  The sound track of a television program, including commercials. The labels on the source tapes indicate this comes from WBBM-TV.
  The program is a discussion on several local issues to Chicago, such as, but not limited to, schools, busing, and funding the police and fire departments.
  There are occasional drop-outs in the audio, such as around 24:20 in part 3. These are heard on the source tapes.
- "Songs for Presidents: A Musical History of America's Major Political Campaigns from 1800 Through 1960,", 1 disc (Record cabinet)
- Chicago Vocational High School spring music festival, 12-inch vinyl LP disc (Record cabinet)
- Philips high school choir and band, 12-inch vinyl LP disc (Record cabinet)
- The Mikado starring Groucho Marx, 12-inch vinyl LP disc (Record cabinet)
- Eisenhower in Asia / Kruschev in America, 12-inch vinyl LP disc (Record cabinet)
- 19?? November 22, 12-inch vinyl LP disc (Record cabinet)
- Chicago public schools orchestra and chorus assisted by the Chicago Symphony Orchestra music recordings, 1959 December (Record cabinet)
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0005684
  Fantasia by Walter Hendl. Hymn to Democracy by Howard Hanson. Walter Hendl conducts both selections. 12-inch lacquer disc.
- H. Miller air check sound recording, 1963 January 18 (Record cabinet)
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0005685
  Miller defends Benjamin Willis as an outstanding school administrator, pointing out that Massachusetts hiring Willis from his current job in Chicago is a compliment to the city. Recorded by WIND radio. 10-inch lacquer disc.
- Benjamin Willis speech: "Start School, When School Starts,", 1961 August 31 (Record cabinet)
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0005686
  Willis asks every boy and girl to enroll in school and stay in school. 10-inch lacquer disc.
- Party at Houston's and other miscellaneous sound recordings, 1947 July 17 - 1950 July 11 (Record cabinet)
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0005687
  11 July 1950: The school board of Yonkers pays tribute to Benjamin Willis as he relocates to Buffalo. Part 1, Bill Dickson, Wm Lally, John Class; Part 2, Wm Lally, B.C.W.; Part 3, B.C.W., Class; Part 4, Class, Collins; Part 5, Collins, Sheets, Burke, Riley; Part 6, Minnervini, Elkind, Campion; Part 7, Rachel, singing "Auld Lang Syne" and "For He's a Jolly Good Fellow".
  Part 8 on 17 July 1947: Officials of Yonkers, New York introduce Benjamin Willis, the recent appointee as school superintendent. Speakers are George Schiele, John Class, Hilda; Part 9, Hilda, Rachel Jr.; Part 10, Rachel Hons of Rest. Taken from original sleeves with speaker information written on them.
  Set of five 12-inch lacquer discs.
- William C. Diehl farewell speech for Benjamin Willis, 1947 June 9 (Record cabinet)
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0005688
  William C. Diehl delivers a speech about Benjamin Willis on the occasion of Willis' departure for a new job. Prior to Mr. Diehl's address, Mrs. Irene Hutzell offers a brief address to Willis concerning a gift from his office. 12-inch lacquer disc.
- Washington County Hillbillies musical performance of Mr. Willis Said, 1947 April 7 (Record cabinet)
  Use copy reference number: 82064_a_0005689
  This is about Benjamin Willis' work with the Washington County schools. 12-inch lacquer disc.